In my lab, we build autonomous aerial robots
في مختبري، نحن نبني روبوتات جوية مستقلة
like the one you see flying here.
مثل الذي ترونه يحلق هنا.
Unlike the commercially available drones that you can buy today,
وخلافا للطائرات بدون طيار المتاحة تجاريا التي يمكنك شراءها اليوم،
this robot doesn't have any GPS on board.
هذا الروبوت لا يمتلك نظام تحديد المواقع.
So without GPS,
فبدون GPS
it's hard for robots like this to determine their position.
من الصعب على هذه الروبوتات تحديد موقعها.
This robot uses onboard sensors, cameras and laser scanners,
يمتلك هذا الروبوت أجهزة استشعار، كاميرات و ماسحات ضوئية ليزرية،
to scan the environment.
لمسح البيئة المحيطة به.
It detects features from the environment,
فتُحدد معالم البيئة حولها،
and it determines where it is relative to those features,
و توضح أين هو بالنسبة لتلك المعالم،
using a method of triangulation.
باستخدام طريقة الإحداثيات.
And then it can assemble all these features into a map,
وبعد ذلك يمكنها تجميع كل هذه المعالم في خريطة،
like you see behind me.
كالتي ترونها ورائي.
And this map then allows the robot to understand where the obstacles are
وهذه الخريطة تسمح للروبوت بتحديد مكان العقبات
and navigate in a collision-free manner.
و التنقل بنمط خالي من التصادم.
What I want to show you next
ما أريد أن أريكم تاليا
is a set of experiments we did inside our laboratory,
هو مجموعة من التجارب أجريناها داخل المختبر
where this robot was able to go for longer distances.
حيث كان الروبوت قادرًا على الذهاب لمسافات أطول.
So here you'll see, on the top right, what the robot sees with the camera.
ترون هنا في أعلى اليمين، ما يراه الروبوت بالكاميرا.
And on the main screen --
وعلى الشاشة الرئيسية
and of course this is sped up by a factor of four --
وبالطبع هذا أسرع أربع أضعاف
on the main screen you'll see the map that it's building.
على الشاشة الرئيسية سترى الخريطة التي تُبنى.
So this is a high-resolution map of the corridor around our laboratory.
لذلك هذه خريطة عالية الدقة للممر حول مختبرنا.
And in a minute you'll see it enter our lab,
و في دقيقة سترونه يدخل المختبر،
which is recognizable by the clutter that you see.
الذي يتم التعرف عليه من خلال الفوضى التي ترونها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the main point I want to convey to you
الفكرة التي أريد إيصالها إليكم
is that these robots are capable of building high-resolution maps
أن هذه الروبوتات قادرة علي بناء خرائط بدقة عالية.
at five centimeters resolution,
بدقة 5 سنتميترات.
allowing somebody who is outside the lab, or outside the building
تمكّن الشخص خارج المختبر او خارج المبني
to deploy these without actually going inside,
من الإنتشار في الداخل دون الدخول فعليًا،
and trying to infer what happens inside the building.
ومحاولة إستنتاج ما يحدث بالداخل.
Now there's one problem with robots like this.
لكن هناك مشاكل لهذه الروبوتات.
The first problem is it's pretty big.
المشكلة الأولى حجمها الكبير
Because it's big, it's heavy.
ولأنها كبيرة، فهي ثقيلة.
And these robots consume about 100 watts per pound.
وهي تستهلك 100 واط للرطل الواحد.
And this makes for a very short mission life.
وهذا يجعل وقت المهمة قصير جدًا.
The second problem
المشكلة الثانية
is that these robots have onboard sensors that end up being very expensive --
هذه الروبوتات على متنها أجهزة إستشعار مكلفة جدا
a laser scanner, a camera and the processors.
ماسحة ليزر وكاميرا ومعالجات.
That drives up the cost of this robot.
وهذا يزيد من سعرها.
So we asked ourselves a question:
لذلك سألنا أنفسنا:
what consumer product can you buy in an electronics store
ماهي المنتجات التي يمكن شراؤها من متجر الإليكترونيات
that is inexpensive, that's lightweight, that has sensing onboard and computation?
التي سعرها رخيص وخفيفة الوزن وبها أجهزة إستشعار ومعالج؟
And we invented the flying phone.
فإخترعنا هاتف طائر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this robot uses a Samsung Galaxy smartphone that you can buy off the shelf,
هذا الروبوت يستخدم هاتف Samsung Galaxy الذي يمكنك شراؤه من المتجر
and all you need is an app that you can download from our app store.
وكل ما تحتاجه هو تطبيق يمكنك تحميله من متجر التطبيقات.
And you can see this robot reading the letters, "TED" in this case,
كما تري هذا الروبوت يقرأ أحرف "TED"
looking at the corners of the "T" and the "E"
ينظر إلى حواف الأحرف "T" و "E"
and then triangulating off of that, flying autonomously.
وبناءًا على إحداثياتها يحلق بشكل مستقل.
That joystick is just there to make sure if the robot goes crazy,
عصا التحكم تلك فقط للتأكد حتى لا يصبح الروبوت مهتاجًا،
Giuseppe can kill it.
جيوسيب يمكن أن تدمره.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In addition to building these small robots,
بالإضافة للمباني، هذه الربوتات الصغيرة،
we also experiment with aggressive behaviors, like you see here.
لديها تجربة مع السلوك العدواني، كما ترون هنا.
So this robot is now traveling at two to three meters per second,
فهذا الربوت يتحرك بسرعة 2 إلى 3 أمتار في الثانية،
pitching and rolling aggressively as it changes direction.
يتأرجح ويدور بعدوانية كلما يغيّر الإتجاه.
The main point is we can have smaller robots that can go faster
الفكرة هنا، يمكن أن يكون لدينا روبوتات أصغر وأسرع
and then travel in these very unstructured environments.
وبالتالي يمكنها التحرك في البيئات الغير منتظمة.
And in this next video,
في الفيديو التالي،
just like you see this bird, an eagle, gracefully coordinating its wings,
كما ترون هذا الطائر، نسر ينسق برشاقة بين جناحيه
its eyes and feet to grab prey out of the water,
وعينيه وقدميه، لينتزع فريسته من الماء،
our robot can go fishing, too.
روبوتنا يمكنه الإصطياد أيضًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In this case, this is a Philly cheesesteak hoagie that it's grabbing out of thin air.
هنا، هذه شريحة جبن فيلي يتم انتزاعها من مكانها
So you can see this robot going at about three meters per second,
إذًا يمكنكم رؤية هذا الربوت يطير بسرعة 3 م/ث،
which is faster than walking speed, coordinating its arms, its claws
( أسرع من الإنسان) منسقًا أذرعه ومخالبه،
and its flight with split-second timing to achieve this maneuver.
في رحلة بدقة زمنية متناهية لينجز المناورة.
In another experiment,
في تجربة أخرى،
I want to show you how the robot adapts its flight
أريد أن أريكم كيف يكيف الربوت تحليقه
to control its suspended payload,
ليتحكم في حمولته المتدلية
whose length is actually larger than the width of the window.
التي طولها أكبر من عرض النافذة
So in order to accomplish this,
لذلك حتى يكمل هذا الدخول
it actually has to pitch and adjust the altitude
عليه أن يتأرجح ويعدل إرتفاعه
and swing the payload through.
ويدخل حمولته من خلالها.
But of course we want to make these even smaller,
لكننا بالطبع نريد أن نجعل هذا الربوت أصغر حجمًا
and we're inspired in particular by honeybees.
وقد ألهمنا نحل العسل تحديدًا.
So if you look at honeybees, and this is a slowed down video,
لأنك إذا نظرت للنحل، (فديو بالعرض البطيء)
they're so small, the inertia is so lightweight --
فهو صغير جدا ، ووزنه خفيف جدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that they don't care -- they bounce off my hand, for example.
لذلك لا يهتمون إذا طردتهم بيدي، على سبيل المثال.
This is a little robot that mimics the honeybee behavior.
هذا ربوت صغير، يقلد سلوك النحل.
And smaller is better,
والأصغر أفضل
because along with the small size you get lower inertia.
لأنك مع الحجم الصغير تحصل أيضا على قصور ذاتي أقل.
Along with lower inertia --
ومع القصور الذاتي الصغير
(Robot buzzing, laughter)
(الروبوت يزن ، ضحك)
along with lower inertia, you're resistant to collisions.
مع القصور الذاتي الصغير تصبح مقاوم للإصطدام.
And that makes you more robust.
وهذا يجعلك أكثر قوة.
So just like these honeybees, we build small robots.
لذلك قمنا ببناء روبوتات صغيرة كالنحل.
And this particular one is only 25 grams in weight.
وهذا الروبوت الذي ترونه وزنه 25 جرام.
It consumes only six watts of power.
يستهلك فقط 6 واط في الساعة.
And it can travel up to six meters per second.
ويمكنه التحليق بسرعة 6 م/ث
So if I normalize that to its size,
لو عايرنا هذا بحجمه
it's like a Boeing 787 traveling ten times the speed of sound.
فإنه كطائرة بوينغ 787 تطير بعشرة أضعاف سرعة الضوء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I want to show you an example.
أريد أن أريكم مثالًا.
This is probably the first planned mid-air collision, at one-twentieth normal speed.
هذا من المحتمل أول إرتطام في الجو مخطط له بسرعة 1/20 من المعدل الطبيعي.
These are going at a relative speed of two meters per second,
الذي سيحدث بسرعة 2 م/ث ،
and this illustrates the basic principle.
وهذا يوضح المبدأ الأساسي
The two-gram carbon fiber cage around it prevents the propellers from entangling,
فالقفص الكربوني حول المراوح الذي يزن جرامين، يحميها من التشابك.
but essentially the collision is absorbed and the robot responds to the collisions.
لكن التصادم يتم إمتصاصه، والروبوت يستجيب لهذا التصادم.
And so small also means safe.
وصغير جدًا مما يعني آمن.
In my lab, as we developed these robots,
في مختبرنا وبينما نطور هذه الروبوتات،
we start off with these big robots
إبتدأنا بهذه الروبوتات الكبيرة.
and then now we're down to these small robots.
وها نحن الآن في النهاية وصلنا لهذه الروبوتات الصغيرة.
And if you plot a histogram of the number of Band-Aids we've ordered
وإذا رسمت رسم بياني لعدد الإسعافات التي طلبناها في الماضي
in the past, that sort of tailed off now.
فقد تلاشت الآن.
Because these robots are really safe.
لأن هذه الروبوتات فعلًا آمنة.
The small size has some disadvantages,
الحجم الصغير له بعض العيوب،
and nature has found a number of ways to compensate for these disadvantages.
والطبيعة قد إكتشفت عدد من الطرق لتعويض هذه العيوب.
The basic idea is they aggregate to form large groups, or swarms.
الفكرة الأساسية أنها تتجمع في مجموعات كبيرة أو أسراب.
So, similarly, in our lab, we try to create artificial robot swarms.
بالمثل في مختبرنا حاولنا خلق سرب صناعي من الروبوتات.
And this is quite challenging
وهذا كان تحديًا كبيرًا
because now you have to think about networks of robots.
لأنك الآن يجب أن تفكر في شبكات من الربوتات
And within each robot,
وداخل كل روبوت،
you have to think about the interplay of sensing, communication, computation --
يجب أن تفكر في التفاعل والإستشعار والتواصل والحساب
and this network then becomes quite difficult to control and manage.
وبالتالي هذه الشبكة يصبح من الصعب التحكم فيها وإدارتها
So from nature we take away three organizing principles
لقد إخذنا من الطبيعة 3 مباديء تنظيمية
that essentially allow us to develop our algorithms.
حيث سمحت لنا بتطوير خوارزمياتنا.
The first idea is that robots need to be aware of their neighbors.
الفكرة الأولى أن الربوت يحتاج أن يكون مدركا لجيرانه.
They need to be able to sense and communicate with their neighbors.
يحتاج أن يكون قادرا على التواصل معهم.
So this video illustrates the basic idea.
لذلك هذا الفيديو يوضح الفكرة الأساسية.
You have four robots --
لديك 4 ربوتات
one of the robots has actually been hijacked by a human operator, literally.
أحد الروبوتات يتحكم فيه شخص.
But because the robots interact with each other,
ولأن الروبوتات تتفاعل مع بعضها البعض.
they sense their neighbors,
فإنها تشعر بجيرانها،
they essentially follow.
وتتابع بعضها.
And here there's a single person able to lead this network of followers.
وهنا شخص واحد قادر على قيادة هذه الشبكة من الأتباع.
So again, it's not because all the robots know where they're supposed to go.
وهذا ليس لأنها جميعها تعرف إلى أين يجب تتجه.
It's because they're just reacting to the positions of their neighbors.
ولكن لأنها فقط تتفاعل مع موقع جيراتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the next experiment illustrates the second organizing principle.
التجربة التالية تشرح المبدأ التنظيمي الثاني.
And this principle has to do with the principle of anonymity.
وهذا المبدأ يأتي مع مبدأ إخفاء الهوية.
Here the key idea is that
الفكرة الرئيسية هنا
the robots are agnostic to the identities of their neighbors.
أن الروبوتات تُنكر هويات جيرانها.
They're asked to form a circular shape,
إذا طُلب منهم تشكيل شكل دائري،
and no matter how many robots you introduce into the formation,
لا يهم العدد الذي أدرجته في التشكيل،
or how many robots you pull out,
أو كم عدد الروبوتات التي أخرجتها.
each robot is simply reacting to its neighbor.
ببساطة كل روبوت يتفاعل مع جاره.
It's aware of the fact that it needs to form the circular shape,
إنها مدركة تماما لحقيقة أنها يجب أن تشكل شكل دائري،
but collaborating with its neighbors
ولكن بالتعاون مع جيرانها
it forms the shape without central coordination.
وتكون الشكل بدون إحداثيات مركزية.
Now if you put these ideas together,
لو قمنا الآن بوضع هذه الأفكار سوية،
the third idea is that we essentially give these robots
فالفكرة الثالثة هي أننا نعطي هذه الروبوتات
mathematical descriptions of the shape they need to execute.
وصف رياضي للشكل الذي عليها إنشائه.
And these shapes can be varying as a function of time,
وهذه الأشكال يمكن أن تتغير مع الزمن،
and you'll see these robots start from a circular formation,
وسترى هذه الروبوتات تبدأ بالشكل الدائري
change into a rectangular formation, stretch into a straight line,
مرورا بالشكل المثلث ثم تنبسط في خط مستقيم،
back into an ellipse.
لتعود للشكل البيضاوي.
And they do this with the same kind of split-second coordination
وهي تفعل هذا بنفس نوع التنسيق الزمني
that you see in natural swarms, in nature.
الذي نراه في أسراب الطيور علي الطبيعة.
So why work with swarms?
إذا لماذا نعمل علي الأسراب؟
Let me tell you about two applications that we are very interested in.
دعوني أخبركم عن تطبيقين نحن مهتمون بهما.
The first one has to do with agriculture,
الأول يتعلق بالزراعة،
which is probably the biggest problem that we're facing worldwide.
التي من المحتمل أنها أكبر مشكلة تواجهنا علي نطاق العالم.
As you well know,
كما تعلمون جيدًا،
one in every seven persons in this earth is malnourished.
واحد من كل 7 أشخاص في هذا الكوكب مصاب بسوء التغذية.
Most of the land that we can cultivate has already been cultivated.
معظم الأراضي التي يمكننا زراعتها هي بالفعل قد زُرعت.
And the efficiency of most systems in the world is improving,
وكفاءة معظم الأنظمة في العالم في تحسُن مستمر،
but our production system efficiency is actually declining.
لكن كفاءة نظامنا الإنتاجي في الحقيقة تنخفض.
And that's mostly because of water shortage, crop diseases, climate change
وهذا غالبا بسبب شُح المياه و أمراض البذور وتغير المناخ
and a couple of other things.
وبعض الأشياء الأخرى.
So what can robots do?
إذا ماذا يمكن أن تفعل الربوتات؟
Well, we adopt an approach that's called Precision Farming in the community.
حسنا، لقد تبنينا منهجا أسميناه "Precision Farming" الإحكام الزراعي في المجتمع،
And the basic idea is that we fly aerial robots through orchards,
والفكرة الأساسية له أن الربوتات تحلق عبر البساتين،
and then we build precision models of individual plants.
ثم نبني نماذج دقيقة لكل نبتة.
So just like personalized medicine,
تماما مثل الطب البشري،
while you might imagine wanting to treat every patient individually,
قد تتخيلون أننا نريد علاج كل مريض على حدة،
what we'd like to do is build models of individual plants
لكن ما نود فعله، أننا نريد بناء نماذج فردية للنباتات
and then tell the farmer what kind of inputs every plant needs --
ثم نخبر المزارع بما تحتاجه كل نبتة.
the inputs in this case being water, fertilizer and pesticide.
في هذه الحالة النبتة تحتاج ماء وسماد ومبيدات حشرية.
Here you'll see robots traveling through an apple orchard,
هنا سترى الروبوت يطير عبر بستان من تفاح،
and in a minute you'll see two of its companions
وبعد دقيقة ترى إثنان من رفقائه
doing the same thing on the left side.
يفعلان نفس الشيء في الجانب الأيسر.
And what they're doing is essentially building a map of the orchard.
ما تفعله الربوتات ببساطة أنها تبني خريطة للبستان.
Within the map is a map of every plant in this orchard.
وداخل الخريطة خريطة لكل نبتة في البستان.
(Robot buzzing)
(طنين الربوت)
Let's see what those maps look like.
دعونا نرى كيف تبدو هذه الخرائط.
In the next video, you'll see the cameras that are being used on this robot.
في الفيديو القادم سترون الكاميرات التي تستخدم علي هذا الروبوت.
On the top-left is essentially a standard color camera.
في أعلى اليسار كاميرا أساسية ملونة.
On the left-center is an infrared camera.
في منتصف اليسار كاميرا أشعة تحت الحمراء.
And on the bottom-left is a thermal camera.
وفي أسفل اليسار كاميرا حرارية.
And on the main panel, you're seeing a three-dimensional reconstruction
وعلي الشاشة الرئيسية ترون بنية ثلاثية الأبعاد
of every tree in the orchard as the sensors fly right past the trees.
لكل شجرة في البستان حينما تعبر منها أجهزة الإستشعار.
Armed with information like this, we can do several things.
متسلحين بمثل هذه المعلومات، يمكن أن نفعل العديد من الأشياء.
The first and possibly the most important thing we can do is very simple:
الشي الأول والأهم الذي يمكننا فعله بسيط جدًا:
count the number of fruits on every tree.
حساب عدد الثمار في كل شجرة.
By doing this, you tell the farmer how many fruits she has in every tree
بفعلك لهذا فإنك تخبر المزارع كم ثمرة لديه في كل شجرة
and allow her to estimate the yield in the orchard,
وبهذا تعطيه القدرة على تقدير المحصول في البستان،
optimizing the production chain downstream.
وتحسين الإنتاجية ليواكب التيار.
The second thing we can do
الشيء الثاني الذي يمكننا فعله هو
is take models of plants, construct three-dimensional reconstructions,
أخذ نماذج النباتات وإنشاء أشكال ثلاثية الأبعاد،
and from that estimate the canopy size,
ومنها تقدير حجم ظل الشجرة،
and then correlate the canopy size to the amount of leaf area on every plant.
ثم ربط حجم الظل بحجم مساحة الورقة في كل شجرة.
And this is called the leaf area index.
وهذا يسمي مؤشر مساحة الورقة.
So if you know this leaf area index,
فإذا عرفت هذا المؤشر،
you essentially have a measure of how much photosynthesis is possible in every plant,
تستطيع معرفة كمية عملية التمثيل الضوئي المحتمل في كل نبتة.
which again tells you how healthy each plant is.
الذي يخبرك مرة أخرى مدي صحيّة كل نبتة.
By combining visual and infrared information,
أيضًا عبر الجمع بين البيانات البصرية وتحت الحمراء،
we can also compute indices such as NDVI.
يمكننا إحصاء المؤشرات مثل (NDVI) المؤشر الموحد لتباين الغطاء النباتي.
And in this particular case, you can essentially see
وفي هذه الحالة بالتحديد يمكنك أن ترى
there are some crops that are not doing as well as other crops.
أن هنالك بعض المحاصيل ليست جيدة كالأخرى.
This is easily discernible from imagery,
هذا يمكن تمييزه بسهولة من الصور،
not just visual imagery but combining
ليس فقط الصور البصرية،
both visual imagery and infrared imagery.
ولكن بتكامل كلاهما البصرية وتحت الحمراء.
And then lastly,
وأخيرًا،
one thing we're interested in doing is detecting the early onset of chlorosis --
شيء نحن مهتمون به وهو الكشف المبكر عن الإصابة في الإخضرار.
and this is an orange tree --
هذه شجرة برتقال
which is essentially seen by yellowing of leaves.
كما ترون إصفرار الأوراق.
But robots flying overhead can easily spot this autonomously
والروبوتات تطير فوقها ويمكنها إكتشاف ذلك بشكل تلقائي
and then report to the farmer that he or she has a problem
تم ترسل تقريرًا للمزارع بأنه لديه مشكلة
in this section of the orchard.
في هذا الجزء من البستان.
Systems like this can really help,
أنظمة كهذه يمكنها فعلًا مساعدتنا.
and we're projecting yields that can improve by about ten percent
ونتصور أن المحاصيل يمكن أن تتحسن بنسبة 10%
and, more importantly, decrease the amount of inputs such as water
والأهم تخفيض المنصرفات، كالماء بنسبة 25%
by 25 percent by using aerial robot swarms.
عند إستخدام أسراب الروبوتات الطائرة
Lastly, I want you to applaud the people who actually create the future,
أخيرًا، أود منكم تحية الفريق الذي إكتشف المستقبل
Yash Mulgaonkar, Sikang Liu and Giuseppe Loianno,
ياش مولغونكار وسكانغ ليو وجوزيف لويانو،
who are responsible for the three demonstrations that you saw.
المسؤولون عن الثلاثة أمثلة التي رأيتموها.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)